Robert D. Smith Papers, 1959-1919, undated
Elmira College
Robert D. Smith Papers, 1959-1919, undated
1919 - 1959
The Robert D. Smith Papers document Smith’s involvement with community organizing in Chicago, Washington, D.C. and Schoharie County, New York from the 1960’s to the 1990’s. The bulk of the papers are community proposals and articles pertaining to community organization. Smith’s experiences related through articles and reports as well as his documented association with Saul Alinsky are highlights of the collection.
.42 linear feet (1 box)
Robert D. Smith
Elmira College Archives, Gannett-Tripp Library, Elmira College, Elmira, N.Y.
Unrestricted
As part of his post-seminary work, Reverend Robert D. Smith, was appointed to the Northwest Community Organization in Chicago, Illinois as a community organization trainee in 1963. Five year later, Smith would accept a job as the Executive Director of the Capitol East Foundation in Washington, D. C.
In the early 1970’s, Smith moved to Schoharie County in New York State. He continued his involvement in community issues in the region into the 1990’s.
Robert D. Smith currently lives in Elmira, N.Y.
Smith, Robert D.; Alinsky, Saul David, 1909-1972; Industrial Areas Foundation; Community organization; personal correspondence
The papers document Smith’s career as a community organizer. The collection contains community proposals and articles written by various organizers primarily during the 1960’s. The proposals are from Smith’s time in Chicago, Washington D.C. and Schoharie County in New York State. Correspondence and other personal related documents are a small subset of the papers. The articles and reports written by Smith as well as news clippings are essential in understanding Smith’s role in community organization from the 1960’s to the 1990’s.
Of note in the papers are Smith’s collection of materials on Saul Alinsky, including letters and memos from his Alinsky and Alinsky’s office.
ORGANIZATIONAL NOTE: The collection has a loose chronological organization, starting with Smith’s work in Chicago in the early 60’s, Washington, D.C. in the late 60’s and Schoharie County in the early 1970’s to the early 1990’s. The collection remains in original order.
- Bibliography for Community Organization [undated] (Box-folder 1 1)
- Strategies for Change: What Are Blocks to Change? How to Avoid Alienation of Humans -- Douglas Still, includes, Enriched Bread, Summer 1965 issue [1965-1967] (Box-folder 1 2)
- Citizen Participation and Community Organization in Planning and Urban Renewal -- Saul Alinsky [1962-1965] (Box-folder 1 3)
- Woodlawn Cooperative Project -- A proposal [1959] (Box-folder 1 4)
- Two Years Inside an IAF (Industrial Areas Foundation) Project -- Draft written by Robert Smith [undated] (Box-folder 1 5)
- Memo - Alinsky to staff [undated] (Box-folder 1 6)
- Post-Graduate Intern Program: Board of National Missions -- Includes correspondence confirming Smith's appointment as a Community Organizer [1961-1963, undated] (Box-folder 1 7)
- Northeast Community Organization -- Smith's reports and other materials [1964, undated] (Box-folder 1 8)
- Northeast Community Organization Resolutions [1965] (Box-folder 1 9)
- Article NCO for "Presbyterian Life" [1965] (Box-folder 1 10)
- NCO Dinner Dance -- Program [1965] (Box-folder 1 11)
- Northeastern Community Organization -- News clippings [1964, undated] (Box-folder 1 12)
- Saul D. Alinsky -- clippings, articles and "Basic Principles of Saul D. Alinsky" by William Lester, includes "Behind the Mask" by Saul Alinsky [1964-1969, undated] (Box-folder 1 13)
- The Church and Neighborhood Community Organization -- Thomas D. Sherrard and Richard C. Murray -- Article [1965] (Box-folder 1 14)
- Hard Talk on Organizing the Ghetto -- Nicholas Von Hoffman [undated] (Box-folder 1 15)
- Power Based Independent Democratic Community Organization -- Robert D. Smith, typescript [undated] (Box-folder 1 16)
- Community Organization in Washington D.C. -- Paul Offner, reprint [1968] (1 17)
- Community Organization clippings -- incl.articles on Alinsky and the Chicago work in the 60's, issues of the Northwest Community Observer, oversize materials in OS1:2 [1960-1975] (Box-folder 1 18)
- Correspondence-- incl. Robert Kennedy [1967-1968] (Box-folder 1 19)
- Capitol East - Proposal for Community Development [1967, undated] (Box-folder 1 20)
- Capitol East Foundation - By-Laws [1967] (Box-folder 1 21)
- Development & Concern of Capitol East [undated] (Box-folder 1 22)
- Capitol East Business & Industrial Investment Assoc.[undated] (Box-folder 1 23)
- Proposal for Development and Expansion of Eastern H.S. Freedom School [undated] (Box-folder 1 24)
- Position Paper on 15th & East Capitol St. N.E. Car Barn Site [undated] (Box-folder 1 25)
- Capitol East Proposal for Truancy and Schools [undated] (Box-folder 1 26)
- Capitol East Community Organization's Program for Black Economics in Capitol East D.C. [1969] (Box-folder 1 27)
- Ghetto Development Corporation -- Proposal [undated] (Box-folder 1 28)
- Proposal for Community Organization in Tacoma Park - East Silver Spring [undated] (Box-folder 1 29)
- Schoharie County -- Correspondence, proposals and materials related to Robert Smith's work in the county [1971-1991, undated] (Box-folder 1 30)